Guide to the Collection of Norwegian Bookplates
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Norwegian Bookplates
1743-1960
BKP 12
Yale University Arts Library
1.67
(4 boxes)
The collection consists of bookplates commissioned by Norwegian individuals and institutions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011 it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of both private and institutional bookplates from Norway as well as ephemeral materials related to the collection.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Bookplates - Individuals. II. Bookplates - Organizations, Institutions, and Businesses. III. Correspondence and Ephemera. The arrangement preserves the original alphabetical ordering by which special letters and those with diacritical marks were sorted at the end of the alphabet. Any correspondence or ephemeral materials relating to a specific bookplate are filed together with the bookplate.
Bookplates, Norwegian; Bookplates
- Bookplates – Individuals, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by the patron's surname.
  - Aaræs – Berg, 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bergsjø – Bränden, 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bråten – Eidheim, 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Else – Frisholm, 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Frossum – Gyllenhammar, 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - H – Hauff, 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hauge – Helland, 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hermansen – Høyer-Finn, 14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jackhelln – Kaas, 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kaifiell – Krüger, 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kvam – Larsen, 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Leine – Menighed, 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Meyer – Paulsen, 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pedersen – Ræder, 16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Røe – Skauge, 19 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Skullerud, Solveig – Skullerud, Ven, 20 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Solberg – Sundbo, 17 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sunby – Tonsberg, 17 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Tossebro – Wangestad, 19 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Waaktaar – Wolli, 6 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Bookplates – Organizations, Institutions, and Businesses, Series II
  A collection of various library, university, social organization, and business bookplates arranged alphabetically.
  - Amstelodami, Bibliotheca Norvegica – Fra Nordmenn I Amerika, 13 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Oslo, Unversitestsbiblioteket – Vestlandske Kunstindustri Museum, 11 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Correspondence and Ephemera, Series III
  This series contains correspondence and other materials without attached bookplates.
  - Postcard; Book: Norske Ex Libris Signaturer (1948), 2 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    General note
    Postcard 195[?] Jan 18 to Admiral & Mrs. E. M. Pace, Jr.
    Book inscribed on inside front cover, "To- Mrs. Edmund Andrews"; possibly signed by the author [Schyberg]. Also pasted onto the inside front cover is a bookplate of Irene Dwen Pace, designed and signed by Herbert Ott.
- 2015 Addition
  Organized into three subseries: Patrons, Artists, and Duplicates.
  - Patrons
    Arranged alphabetically by the bookplate patron.
    - Aarnaes – Baklund, 1942-1952; 21 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Barman – Berulfsen, 1943-1948 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bibliotheca Norvegica – Brataas, 1926-1946 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bredahl – Diesen, 1884-1948 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Disch – Evensen, 1939-1953 undated; 21 items (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Falck – Friis, 1942-1948 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Frimann – Gogstad, 1938-1942 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Gripsrud – Halvorsen, 1926-1949 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hansen – Hennum, 1902-1945 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hermansen – Ihlen, 1922-1950 undated; 21 items (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Iversen – Jebsen, 1923-1958 undated; 19 items (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Jenssen – Kongsvold, 1903-1946; 20 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - König – Lörup, 1940-1945 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Lowstrom – Noreger, 1941-1946 undated; 20 items (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Norsk – Ramberg, 1928-1949 undated; 21 items (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Ramstad – Skarløv, 1944-1946 undated; 17 items (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Skjelle – Söhol, 1944-1949 undated; 20 items (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Sörböe – Wattne, 1926-1945 undated; 20 items (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Weller – Wolli, 1947 undated; 8 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Artists
    Arranged alphabetically by the artist's name, then alphabetically by patron within each artist's folder.
    - Schjaerven [J–Lil], 1937-1953 undated; 20 items (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Schjaerven [Lin–M], 1942-1959 undated; 19 items (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Schjaerven [N–Rei], 1937-1952 undated; 22 items (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Schjaerven [Rek–Sk], 1932-1950 undated; 20 items (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Schjaerven [Sl–Sø], 1925-1949 undated; 20 items (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Schjaerven [Sö–], 1943-1950 undated; 20 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes a few pamphlets about Schjaerven's ex-libris.
    - Skarløv, 1949-1954 undated; 21 items (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Skaare – Svarstad (excluding Øyvind Sørensen), 1904-1947 undated; 12 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Sørensen [A–He], 1922-1956; 28 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Sørensen [Ho–Li], 1910-1953 undated; 20 items (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Sørensen [Lo–Sö], 1901-1949 undated; 21 items (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Sørensen [T–W], 1902-1947 undated; 18 items (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Yran [A–K], 1944-1946 undated; 21 items (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Yran [M–Y], 1944-1945 undated; 16 items (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Duplicates
    - Norway – Duplicates, 1942 undated; 4 (Box 4, Folder 34)